<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The estate of Christians, liuing vnder the subiection of the Turke And also the warres betweene the Christians and the Turke, beginning 1592. and continuing till the end of 1593.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1595</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 25 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A18686</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 5197</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S109838</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99845482</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99845482</idno>
            <idno type="VID">10387</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A18686)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 10387)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 192:02)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The estate of Christians, liuing vnder the subiection of the Turke And also the warres betweene the Christians and the Turke, beginning 1592. and continuing till the end of 1593.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[24] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by [T. Scarlet for] Iohn Wolfe,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1595.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>"The warres between the Christians and the Turke" has separate title page.</note>
                  <note>Register is continuous.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-C⁴ (C4 blank).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Turkey --  History --  1453-1683.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:10387:1"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:10387:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>THE ESTATE OF CHRISTIANS, liuing vnder the ſubiection <hi>of the Turke.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And alſo the warres betweene the Chriſtians and the Turke, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning 1592. and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuing till the end of 1593.</p>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>printer's or publisher's device</figDesc>
                  </figure>
                  <p>LONDON Printed by IOHN WOLFE. 1595.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:10387:2"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:10387:2"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="account_of_Christians_under_Turkish_rule">
                  <pb facs="tcp:10387:3"/>
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:10387:3"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>The eſtate of Chriſtians, liuing</hi> vnder the ſubiection of the great Turke.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>Iuers Countries and Nations are in ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iection of the Turke, and among the reſt, all Greece, ſaue a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie little parte of it, which is vnder the Segnorie of <hi>Venice:</hi> inſomuch that there be many thouſandes of Chriſtians ſubiect to Turkiſh tyrannie. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of euen the beſt and greateſt are oppreſſed with great toules and taxes, and peſtered with infinit ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tortions and paimentes yeerely. All the male chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of Chriſtians are written vp at the day of their birth, and comming to ten or twelue yeres of their age, are preſented to the Turkes officers, who take all ſuch as they finde well made, and like to proue fit men for ſeruice in warre, from their parents, and conuey them to the Turkes, to bee brought vp in warlike exerciſes, and to become Turkes, and ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:10387:4"/> to God, and their owne fathers and mothers, and kinsfolke, ſtanding the Turke in more ſted than his own naturall people. And for each one of them that the Turks officers leaue at home, not thinking them fit for their turns, muſt be paid yerely as good as eight ſhillinges Engliſh, by their parentes, howe poore ſo euer they be, for they muſt find it or ſmart for it. If anie chriſtian chance in anger or haſtines, (as who is ſo patient as not to be moued beeing ſo ſtinged) hauing receiued wrong, do ſtrike a Turke, he is ſure to be ſo puniſhed, that if he doo liue after, he liueth to lament his life, &amp; to wiſh death. When the Turkes officers come to anie Chriſtians houſe when they go in progreſſe, and make their viſitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, there muſt be great ſtore of cheere, and much coſt prouided to welcome them withall, or they wil be but ill come to the chriſtians that they come vnto. If anie Chriſtian releeue, or giue anie ſuccor, aide or aſſiſtance to another Chriſtian fugitiue, he is taken priſoner, &amp; beſides the loſſe of all his goods and poſſeſſions, kept in extreame miſerie, and moſt barbarouſlie handled till he paie for his ranſome as much as they ſhall appoint. Neither wil the Turks oftentimes be brought to releaſe them for any ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, but after a thouſand martirdomes wrought vpon them, they put them to death. Their puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are diuerſe, ſome Chriſtians are tied hand &amp; foote, and laide on the ground, with a ſtone almoſt of inſupportable waight on their backes. Others are put in gallies, where they be galled in deed and vſed moſt doggedly. Others they tie hand &amp; foote
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:10387:4"/> and laie them on their backes, and let a long rag of cipres or fine linnen dipped in pickle or ſalt water, ſinke by little and litle into their throats, till it reach downe to their ſtomackes, and then they plucke it out againe, and ſo put the poore Chriſtians to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakable paine and torment, When the Turkes haue taken anie Citie or forte of the Chriſtians, or haue ouercome any great armie, they lead all them that they put not moſt cruelly to the ſwoorde, into moſt lamentable captiuity, tormenting them in the foreſaid manner, and inflicting a thouſand woorſe martirdomes vpon them, which I will omit, they requiring a longer diſcourſe: &amp; I will rather praie vnto Almightie God to haue mercie vpon vs, and to defend all good people from the like afflictions. And howbeit that it pleaſeth his diuine maieſtie to puniſh our wickedneſſe with ſuch temporall tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, yet that of his gracious mercifulnes he wold not ſuffer ſo many poore innocent children, being carryed awaie by force to me their fathers offences by looſing their ſouls: with which coſt many chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians beſides are dangerouſly menaced, being part<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly miſ-lead by the vanitie of Turkiſh pompe and pride entiſing them, and partly oppreſſed with po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertie and miſerie, conſtraining them to forſake the true fountaine of life, to drinke of the puddle of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidelitie and paganiſme, therfore to abide euerlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thirſt. Wherefore we are bounden to pray vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Almightie God, to turne awaie ſo much harme from his people, &amp; not only to keep them perpetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally in the way of the truth, that are alredy brought
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:10387:5"/> vnto it, but alſo ſo to lighten the heartes and vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of the blinded, that ſeeing the light of the Goſpell, they may imbrace it, and know that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the cleere Sunne-ſhine of the ſame all light is but darkneſſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="prayer">
                  <head>A praier vnto GOD for the peace of Christendome, to defend and preſerue it from Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiſh inuaſion, to the deſtruction &amp; ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw of all Infidels.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> God Almightie and moſt merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull Father, whoſe power and greatnes is knowen vnto all men, and whoſe glorie ſhineth moſt brightly ouer the whole face of the earth, as the beams of the Sun from the Eaſt to the Weſt, caſt down the eies of thy ſoueraigne mercie on vs poore wretched ſinners, &amp; howbeit we haue by our manifolde wickedneſſes deſerued not onely temporall puniſhment, but alſo euerlaſting damnatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, yet we beſeech thee ô Lord, not to regard our innumerable offences, as in num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, ſo alſo exceeding in greatnes and hainouſnes, but to beſtowe on vs thy moſt gracious and merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full pardon, conſidering that our onely mediatour and thy onely beloued ſonne Ieſus Chriſt hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed vs with his moſt precious bloud, &amp; made ſatisfaction by that moſt acceptable ſacrifice for all our ſinnes &amp; offences. Grant vs therefore thy peace O Lord, and poure downe from heauen on Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:10387:5"/> Princes and the rulers of thy people, thy grace to embrace concord and vnitie, that they being by thee inſpired with wiſedome and heauenly coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels, may ſo gouern the people and maintaine their callinges, that all may bee ſurely defended from Turkes, Infidels, and other enimies of thy faith and moſt holy truth. Suffer not O Lord, the prophane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of thy ſacred Goſpell to inlarge theyr proude dominion and tyrannicall Empire, with the poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſions and territories of thy people. Let not Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gans, and ſuch as ſeek to violate and to ouerthrow thy heauenly conſtitutions and ordinances, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dew the earth with Chriſtian bloud, for the eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing of Idolatry, Superſtition, and Atheiſme. Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit them not moſt mer<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ifull Father, to triumph o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer thy ſeruants, whome they leade into captiuity, allot to the verie worſt manner of bondmanſhip and ſlauerie, and oppreſſe with moſt barbarous and ineffable crueltie. O Lorde, indue our Kinges and rulers with true feeling and vnderſtanding, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider and perpend how dangerouſly we are mena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced and threatned by thoſe that beeing worſe than the worſt of badnes, eſteeme of thy ſeruantes as of dogs, and how like we are to become the ſubiects of theyr wrath and furie, if by thy gracious merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes order be not taken to croſſe their deſſeignes and to deſtroy their purpoſes. Giue vnto our Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines and men of Armes true valour and courage to contemne and ſcorn the force, ſtrength, &amp; pride of their preſumptuous enimies, and to omit no op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunitie of reuenge which may be taken on the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:10387:6"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="5" facs="tcp:10387:6"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="6" facs="tcp:10387:7"/> for their inſulting &amp; perfidious brauery, their ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litious rancor and cankred ſpite. Well do we know O Lord, that our owne pride, ambition, hatred, ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill diſcord, and what not? doeth crie vp vnto hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen for iuſt puniſhment and abundance of wrath, and worlds of vengeance to fall vpon vs for our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtable wickednes. But yet (ô God) whoſe mercie is greater than the ſea is deepe, or heauen high, or the world wide, as being in deede infinite, if not for our ſake, yet for thine owne glories ſake pardon vs, and take from our ſhoulders the heauy burthen of thine anger and indignation, we not being able to conceiue the vnmeaſurable greatnes of the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment which our ſin deſerueth, much leſſe to beare it. For thy honors ſake, and moſt glorious deſerts of thy ſonne our Lord, and the worldes true ſon Ieſus Chriſt, deface the enemies of his Goſpell, eclipſe their vanting, ouerthrow their proud oſtentations of worldly pomp and roialtie. Let them know that thou art the God of heauen and earth, and art plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with nothing but with the true worſhip of thy onely begotten ſonne Ieſus Chriſt, that all pompe, pride and glorie without him, is baſenes and vaine folly, yea, wretchedneſſe and miſerie. Defend thy Church (ô Lord) and let thy people moſt victori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly triumph ouer thy enemie, plant thy truth in all parts of the world, that thy mercie &amp; glory may ouerſhade the earth, and all the inhabitants therof ſing praiſe &amp; honor vnto thy name among all na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and countries from age to age world without end. Amen.</p>
               </div>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:10387:7"/>
                  <p>THE VVARRES BETWEENE THE Chriſtians and the <hi>Turke.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>printer's or publisher's device</figDesc>
                  </figure>
                  <p>LONDON Printed by IOHN WOLFE. 1595.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb facs="tcp:10387:8"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:10387:8"/>
                  <head>THE VVARRES BETWEENE THE <hi>Chriſtians and the Turke.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He yeere 1592, Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zan, Baſſa of Boſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na, beeing Generall of the Turkes, go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out of Boſſena into Croatia, ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dainly beſieged, &amp; within a while toke the towne and Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtell of Wihitz, the which had now 150. yeeres bene a ſtrong and ſure defence for the Chriſtians in that Countrie againſt the Turkes, who after the taking thereof, in fewe dayes built a blocke-houſe and a bridge a litle way of, vpon the riuer Calapis: which being done, they
<pb facs="tcp:10387:9"/> burned and ſpoiled all the Countrie ouer between Calapis and Sauus. This ſoddaine aſſaulte of the Turke, ſtroke great feare into the minds of the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrians and Germanes. But Thomas Erdeud the Ban of Sclauonia, that hee might defend his owne Countrie Thuropoly from theſe inuaſions, muſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring his owne forces, and getting certaine aide of the Auſtrians, and other his neighbours, incamped himſelfe right ouer againſt the forte of Patirnia, which (as earſt I ſayd) the Turkes had lately build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the bridge. There he expected further ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply of men and munition, from the kingdomes of Sclauonia and Croatia. Which things Hazan Baſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſa being certified of, by a trechour, a familiar of the Ban aforeſayd, retired by the neereſt waie, and ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dainly aſſalted the chriſtians, who as yet knew not well what the number &amp; furniture of the enemies were. He came on the rereward with a huge pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, &amp; the horſe men being put to flight, he ſlaughte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the infanterie, and chiefly the Auſtrians, and ſo became maſter of their ordinance.</p>
                  <p>Then marched he forward without impeach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment thorough all Thuropoly, and alonge the moſt populous bankes of Calapis and Sauus, where hee gaue vnto death, and vnto bondage worſe than death about foure thouſand men. Hee thought alſo to haue beene maſter of the caſtle of Siſſek, ſcituate at the concurrent of the two riuers Calapis and Sauus, becauſe it was a fit place for paſſage into Auſtria, Carinthia, and Carniota, a
<pb facs="tcp:10387:9"/> thing which had ſometimes afore bene attempted, but then hee was nobly repulſed by the rare worth of Nicholas Miccatius the gouernour, and the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular valour of the garriſon ſouldiers, ſo that after a fewe idle aſſaultes, hee was forced to giue it o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer.</p>
                  <p>In Summer this preſent yere 1593. Aazan Baſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſa, with certaine of the Sangiacbeges, whereof hee hath nine vnder his commaunde, returning to the beſiege of Siſſek, firſt razing Treſchina, a caſtle of the Biſhop of Zagabria, came before it about the beginning of Iune, &amp; hauing made many breaches by continuall battery night &amp; daie, there was now no hope of ſafetie for the beleaguered, vnleſſe God beyond all thought, had ſuccoured them. For al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though Caſars troupes, which were now muſtered of the Auſtrians, and the borderers thereabouts, were much fewer than the Turkes, yet the Ban of Sclauonia, and Auers Pergius, and Rupertus E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenberger, &amp; diuers other nobles, amongſt whom was Melchior Reder, Baron of Sileſia, a man fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous both for learning and martiall affaires, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing the leading of them.</p>
                  <p>When they behelde and ſawe the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans beſieged, and brought to ſuch diſtreſſe, with heroike worth, and reſolute courage, bringing firſt their armie into Siſſec, they ſallyed out on the Turkes, who had made a bridge ouer Calapis, and pitched theyr Tentes both on this and that ſide of the Riuer: they put them to flight that
<pb facs="tcp:10387:10"/> were on this ſide of the riuer, &amp; making themſelues maſters of a parte of the bridge, they cut it downe, ſo that this part of the Turkes armie coulde not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire to the other, they ſtill periſhed, and driue the retiring Turkes euen to the riuer, who rather com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted themſelues to the mercie of the water, than to the mercie of the victours. The other that were on the other ſide of the water, quite amazed by this ſlaughter of their fellowes, committed their ſafetie to their feete. There were drowned in the riuer, Hazan Baſſa aforeſaid, with his brother, and Sinam Beg or preſident of Cliſta, the ſonne of Amurathes the Turkes ſiſter, and Memy Beg or preſident of Hertzegouin, which was the chiefe Citie of highe Boſsina, ſometime a Dukedome, as Bagnia Luca, the ſeate of Baſſa, was the Metropolis of the kingdome of baſe Boſsina.</p>
                  <p>Amurath the Turke was ſo grieued with this o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerthrowe, wherein his ſiſters ſonne, and the Baſſa of Boſsinas ſelfe, with many other valiaunt men, were either ſlaine or drowned in Calapis, that part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly through the wofull lamentations of his ſiſter, who at his feet deſired reuenge of her ſlain ſonne, and partly by the perſwaſion of Sinam, Baſſa, and partly for the diſdaine and griefe of the aforeſayde ouerthrowe, hee preſently denounced open warre vpon Rodolph the Emperor, and made Mahumet, Baſſa of Temes warre, Deputy of Boſſena &amp; Cro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atia, with authoritie to proſecute the warre, and cauſed the Deputie of Greece to aide him with an
<pb facs="tcp:10387:10"/> armie, and commanded the Baſſa of Buda and the reſt, to put garriſons in the caſtells of the frontries, and to be at the command of Sinam Basſhau of Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirian, whom he ſent as his lieutenant generall into Hungarie.</p>
                  <p>Now the Chriſtians after the Turkes ouerthrow at Siſek, taking reſpite for two moneths, began at laſt, though too late, to beſiege the caſtle Petrinia, neere to Hraſtowiz vpon Calapis, which the Turks had fortified the yere before: for hearing by a Turk a ſpie (who came voluntary vnto them, and ſo at his pleaſure went a waie) that the Deputie of Greece marched thether, though the Turkes in the Caſtle beſieged were in great diſtreſſe, wanting pouder, &amp; conſulting to come to a parlie of ſurrendering the holde, they raiſed their ſiege and departed. When this fame of the Turkiſh warre, renued and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed in Conſtantinople and Buda, was bruited in Germanie, the yeerely penſion which had not beene paide rwo yeeres together, was without de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lay, the firſt daie of Auguſt, carried from Vienna to Gamorrha. But preſently newes came that Sinan Basſhau the Generall, marched into Hungary nere to Buda, &amp; that the forces of the deputie of Greece which were alreadie come into Croatia, had not onelie raiſed the ſiege at Petrinia, but had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo wonne Siſck, and had cruelly maſſacred and put to death all the garriſon ſouldiers, among whome were ſome Germanes, and had throwen their carcaſes into the riuer Calapis, and that after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards
<pb facs="tcp:10387:11"/> paſsing ouer Sauus, euen to Sagabria, ſpoyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing &amp; burning as they went, they had taken about fiue thouſand men, whome they made theyr miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable bond ſlaues, &amp; that the ſiege of Sagabria was expected euerie houre. Therefore they thought it beſt to take ſome other courſe to withdrawe the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemie, and to vndertake a better courage of war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like defence. Therefore there went poſt to Prage Frances Nadaſtus, the noble Duke of Hungarie, &amp; Deputie of Iaurin, Ferdinard Earle of Hardec, and diuerſe others of Auſtria, Carniola, Carinthia, and other places, who did aggrauate the greatneſſe of the danger by reaſon of the Turkes, &amp; complained that vnleſſe they had preſent aides, they ſhoulde of neceſsitie be conſtrained to yeeld vnto them. The Emperour therefore gaue commandement to mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter the Bohemians, Silueſians, Moracians, Auſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, and other of his hereditarie princes, for ſeruice on horſeback and on foot, and to augment the gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſons in the limitanie holds, and ſent Embaſſadors to the electors of the Empire, for the holding of a parliament at Rauenſpurg, for the vniting of the forces of the Empire, to with-holde the Turkiſh crueltie from Germanie, and from other partes of Chriſtendome. He hired alſo great forces of horſe and foote men againſt the next ſpring, becauſe Baſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhaw Sinam hauing taken Weſpria and Palatta, threatned that he would without faile march into Vienna.</p>
                  <p>Ferdinand Samaria, and George Andrew of
<pb facs="tcp:10387:11"/> Hofkirchen were gouernors of Weſtpriu, and had a garriſon of twelue thouſand ſoldiers. Sinam Baſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſa laide ſiege to it the two and twentith of Septem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber: he made three skonces vpon the high waies to Raba and Palatta, in the night he caſt his trenches, and raiſed twelue barricados on them, and began to batter the wall with the Canon, and ſlue the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of the Ordenaunce of Weſtpriu with a ſhot. They did little that daie, and therfore the next daie they intrenched themſelues neerer to the wall, and from ſixe ſeuerall places ſo thundred vppon them, that almoſt no man could ſtand in ſafetie either on the wals or in the fortreſſes. Then after certaine aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaultes to ſcale the wall, they were at laſt repulſed with a large hail of the muskettiers. The next mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning had no ſooner giuen light to the fourth daye of the ſiege, but the Turks fiercely renued the bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie, &amp; hauing ſcaled the wals, they began there to aduance their colours, but our ſouldiers put them to the foile. Being ſo defeated, they threw balles of wilde fire on the gate, and on the wooden houſes adioyning, and razed the wals neere to the gate, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen vnto the grounde: and giuing freſh onſets a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the gate and the caſtle, and other places, they ſo diſcouraged the gouernor and the ſouldiers, that being now deſperate to defend the towne any lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, becauſe there appeared no hope of ſuccor from the gouernours of Raba and Pappa: the night fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing they ſecretly iſſued out of the citie, &amp; ſoght to ſaue themſelues by flight: but the Turks percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing
<pb facs="tcp:10387:12"/> it, purſued them as they fled: many of them they ſlue, and tooke Ferdinand Samaria the gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor himſelfe, and ſome other priſoners.</p>
                  <p>There eſcaped to Pappa in ſafetie about fortie Germanes, and foure and fiftie Hungarians. On Saint Michaels euen the Turkes beſieged Palatta, where two Hungarians that ranne awaie to them, are recorded to haue told them whence the caſtle might beſt bee battered. But whereas the Baſhau hauing ſent letters into the caſtle, wherein hee per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded the garriſon ſouldiers which were foure hundred to yeelde the Caſtle vnto him, ſith it ſhould be a bootleſſe matter to make reſiſtance, &amp; promiſed them life and ſafe conduit if they would departt hauing voluntarily ſurrendred it, they had in deede ſafe conduite for one mil<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, but after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes at a ſigne giuen, they were almoſt all mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered, ſo that of all, only foure &amp; twentie eſcaped.</p>
                  <p>The thinges which followed had better ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe. For when intelligence was giuen by the cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiues and the ſpies which Basſhau Sinam by reaſon of the winter nowe approching, had diſpoſed his armes to their winteringes, and that himſelfe reuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked by Amurath, was gone poaſt to Conſtantino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, becauſe the Perſians and the Georgians had certaine newe complots in hand, Ferdinand Earle of Hardec, Generall of the armie of baſe Hunga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, ioyning to his, the Armies of Peter Huſan go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernour of Pappa, and of Nadaſtus Earle of Serin, and of Palfius, and other Captaines, marched to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes
<pb facs="tcp:10387:12"/> Albie-royall, hauing ſome hope to get the ſuburbes thereof, and the houſe of the gouernor of the Citie, and the demaines. He therefore ſent Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar Peter to the further ſide of the Citie, with com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement that at midnight he ſhould aſſault the ſuburbes, at what time hee himſelfe would giue a ſigne, that he alſo made an aſſault on the other ſide, that ſo they might more eaſily ouercome them, whome they did aſſaile in the ſuburbs, their minds and forces beeing ſo diſtract, and Huſar tooke and burnt one of the ſuburbs, but the Turks defending the Citie, our men thought beſt, beeing deſtitute both of victual &amp; munition, to forſake it: and when as they had ſcarſe retired two miles, the next daie word was brought, that the Turkes in great troups followed them, and were determined to ſet vppon them as they fled. Thereupon our men ſtaie, pauſe vpon the point, marſhall the battell, and beard the enemy to his teeth, fighting valiantly, and God ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king amazement into the enemies heart, they turne the Ianizaries into flight, and obtain a noble victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie the four and twentith of October, according to the olde ſtile. The Aga or Captaine of the Ianiza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries being taken priſoner, reported that the Baſſa of Buda diſſwaded them from fight, but that at laſt he was conſtrained to go out to fight by the importu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie and threates of the ſouldiers. It is thought that hee hauing receiued three woundes with musket ſhot, died afterwardes at Buda. There were in this skirmiſh beſides the Basſhau of Buda, the Sanzach
<pb facs="tcp:10387:13"/> or gouernour of Albie-roiall, of Strigon, of Peſtis, of Fiukirks, of Moach, of Fillek, of Newſtair, of Zeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chen, of Copau, of Zolnock, of Zegedin, &amp;c. But I cannot tell whether anie of them were kilde or no. Ferdinand Earle of Hardec after this victorie at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chieued, returned to Raba in Iaurin.</p>
                  <p>In high Hungarie, Frederike Baron of Tieffen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bach, by force wonne from the Turkes the caſtle of Zabacca, which they had fortified, where reſting onely one daie, he brought his armie before Tillek a famous caſtle and towne, the ſeate of the Turkes Deputie, and two miles from the place aforeſayd. There on the twelfth of Nouember he put to flight the Turkiſh armie, which was raiſed of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries adiacent, and came thether to raiſe the ſiege. The next daie they raiſed their rampires agaynſt the towne, and began to batter it, but the Turkes themſelues burnt that, and abandoning the baſe skonce, the garriſon ſouldiers about eight hundred betooke themſelues to the gard of the high caſtle a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, but at laſt with condition of their liues, they yeelded it by compoſition. The fame of this ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>render, cauſed the Turkes which held the caſtles of Diun and Hamaske neere thereto, to forſake theyr holdes, and vnaſſalted to flie awaie. Then was the armie brought before the towne and caſtle of Zet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chen another holde of the Sangiachag, and wonne it with certaine of her caſtles adioyning, of Holloc, Samos, and Plaueſteine: which the garriſons wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly forſaking lefte, to defend themſelues agaynſt
<pb facs="tcp:10387:13"/> the approching enemie. Towardes the ende of the moneth, Nogard (ſo they commonly call it) and Sangiacaf, a famous towne became ours, and cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine Turkes of Albie-roiall bringing a new Depu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty into the caſtle of Palatte newly ſurpriſed, were in December by Huzar Peter valiantly put to the worſe. But ſith the time of the yeere was ſo vnfit, &amp; the continuall raine made the waies ſo deepe, that their ordinance could not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ueniently be haled fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> place to place, and that the armye could not indure to lie incamped anie longer, they were on both ſides inforced to go to their wintering places. In the meane time Sinam the Baſſa of Veſirium was earneſtly expected at Buda, but he beeing gone to Conſtantinople, the deputy of Greece is recorded to haue come to Buda at laſt with a certaine power not of greateſt importance.</p>
               </div>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
